A Guide to the Bernard Family Papers, 1761-1800
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Bernard Family Papers, 1761-1800
Library of Virginia
20243
29 leaves and 20 pages and 2 volumes
Bernard Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ellen Claiborne Williamson, 5 September 1930
Biographical Information
The Bernards were a prominent family in Buckingham County, Virginia. John Bernard was born in 1736 in Gloucester County, Virginia. He moved to Cumberland County, Virginia, and married Henningham Carrington (1746-1810), the daughter of George Carrington (1711-1785). He moved to Buckingham County where he became one of the county's prominent citizens. He served as sheriff during the 1780s. He and his wife had five children who married into other local prominent families. The Bernards also speculated in lands in Kentucky.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1761-1800, of the Bernard family of Buckingham County, Virginia, consisting of accounts, affidavits, bonds, certificates, commissions, deeds, land grants, letters, lists, plats, powers of attorney, receipts, warrants, and writs. Many of the affidavits, certificates, land grants, letters, lists, plats, and powers of attorney concern the purchase, sale, and ownership of land in Virginia and Kentucky, including two volumes listing military land warrant claims. Other accounts, letters, and lists concern the payment of levies and taxes on land and property in Buckingham County. Two deeds and a receipt refer to the purchases of slaves by John Bernard (1736-1799). Another deed concerns an apprenticeship of Wade Netherland with Samuel Ayres. Some accounts and bonds involve the payment of debts and fees; one bond is security for Cary Drew as deputy sheriff of Buckingham County. Several writs refer to criminal and civil court proceedings in Buckingham County. Two certificates recognize the election of David Bell (d. 1799) and Charles Patteson as delegates to the Virginia ratifying convention in 1788. There is a commission for William Bernard as lieutenant for the 1st Battalion, 24th Regiment, Virginia militia. Also a warrant for the formation of a slave patrol in Buckingham County.
Arrangement
Chronological
Contents List
- Letter, 7 March 1761, George Carrington to John Bernard concerning assignment of land., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Deed, 11 February 1768, for a female slave, from Kemp Plummer of Gloucester County, [Virginia], to John Bernard of Cumberland County, [Virginia]., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Bond, 5 March 1770, from Mary Hardwick to Samuel Jordon, both of Buckingham County, [Virginia] for payment of money owed by Hardwick to Jordan., 2 p., photocopy.
- Account, 25 June 1773, from John Bernard with John Burton of Charlotte County, [Virginia], noting payment for debts dated 1 November 1764 and 18 March 1768 for purchase of beer, rum, and punch., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Writ, 28 August 1777, to the sheriff of Buckingham County to apprehend James Patteson [or Patterson]. Writ based on information from John Bernard that Patteson was trying to "stir up a rebellion among the people" against the newly formed government., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Receipt, 22 February 1780, from W. Cannon to John Bernard for payment for purchase of a male slave., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Deed, 2 April 1783, between John Netherland of Powhatan County, [Virginia], and Samuel Ayres of Buckingham County binding Netherland's son Wade to Ayres as an apprentice to learn carpentry., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Account, May-August 1783, of John Strange and Harding Perkins, executors of Thomas Mitchell, with Edmund Wilcox, Clerk of the Amherst County [Virginia] Court. Payment of legal fees., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Writ, 31 August 1784, from Henry Bell to Joseph Baker, William Wilkerson, and John Toney, ordering them to examine damage done by horses owned by William Nelson and Major Bolling to a cornfield owned by John Bernard., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Account, 1786-1787, of John Bernard with the sheriff of Buckingham County for legal fees., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Deed, 8 May 1787, for a male slave from William Morris to John Bernard, both of Buckingham County., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Land grant, 14 May 1787, for 1,000 acres in the Virginia Military District to Edward Carrington from Lieutenant Governor Beverley Randolph. Includes a survey of the 1,000 acres., 2 p., photocopy.
- Certification, [10 March 1788], by John Bernard, sheriff of Buckingham County, for the election of Charles Patteson and David Bell as delegates to the Virginia Ratifying Convention in June 1788., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Certification, 10 March 1788, by John Bernard, sheriff of Buckingham County, for the election of Charles Patteson and David Bell as delegates to the Virginia Ratifying Convention in June 1788., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- bond, 14 June 1789, from Cary Drew, Benjamin Harrison, and David Bell to John Bernard, sheriff of Buckingham County, for service of Drew as a deputy sheriff., 1 leaf.
- Commission, 13 May 1794, for William Bernard as lieutenant in the 1st Battalion, 24th Regiment of the Virginia militia, signed by Governor James Wood., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Account, 1796, of James Dillard, sheriff of Buckingham County consisting of levies for 1796., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- List, 1796, of sums of money directed to be paid by the sheriff out of the levy for the year 1796, signed by B. Branch deputy clerk of Buckingham County. Includes relavent notations by W. B. Bernard and Rolfe Eldridge, clerk of Buckingham County., 2 p., photocopy.
- Letter, 17 June 1796, from George Mayo to William Bernard, Lexington, Kentucky, stating that he is willing to sell his share of a claim in Kentucky lands., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Letter, 31 August 1796, from Randolph Jefferson to John Bernard requesting information about his payment of taxes on his lands in Buckingham County., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Writ, 17 December 1796, from John Bernard to John Toney of Buckingham County ordering him to search certain homes for a stolen hog. Includes Toney's report, 7 January 1797, stating that he searched the specified homes and found no stolen hog., 2 p., photocopy.
- Account, 1798, of Anthony Winston, sheriff of Buckingham County listing levies for 1797., 2 p., photocopy.
- Certification, 18 July 1797, by Josias Jones, commissioner of Buckingham County, concerning land owned by Henry Godsey and taxes owed., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Request, 2 March 1798, from Ishmael Bailey to the Virginia Land Office requesting a warrant for land due him for Revolutionary War service., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Writ, 23 March 1798, from P. Tinsley, for the High Court of Chancery, to John Bernard, regarding interviews of witnesses in the suit of John Reveley and John Bernard against William Cabell., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Writ, 17 August 1798, from John Bernard to William White, constable of Buckingham County, ordering him to apprehend a slave named Ben and bring him before Bernard as justice of the peace for robbing and threatening another slave named Sam., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Power of attorney, 1 June 1800, from Judith C. Gist of Clarke County, Kentucky, to William Bernard authorizing him to sell a tract of land in Buckingham County left to her in the will of David Bell. This was recorded in Buckingham County Court 8 September 1800., 3 p., photocopy.
- Patrollers' warrant, n.d., issued to John Toney, Jr., Edmond Toney, Francis Wilkinson, and William Taylor to patrol slave quarters and to stop slaves travelling about. Document is unfinished., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Affidavit, n.d., concerning land surveyed before the Revolution for an ensign in the British Army named O'Neal in what is now Kentucky. Includes a survey of 600 acres in Kentucky for one Watkins., 2 p., photocopy.
- Plat, n.d., of 330 acres, possibly in Cumberland County, [Virginia], belonging to Dr. Samuel Wilson., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- list, n.d., of certain land owners and their acreage, possibly in Kentucky., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Affidavit, n.d., of John Breckinridge and George Nicholas concerning a contract made by William Bernard with William Smith, John Mayo, and George Mayo regarding lands in Kentucky., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Plat, n.d., of the connections of the interferences with Mayo's 30,000 acres. This land is in Kentucky., 3 leaves, photocopy
- Plat, n.d., of William Suddoth's connection on John Mayo's 30,000 acres. This land is in Kentucky., 3 leaves, photocopy.
- List, n.d., of military lands, including warrant number, name, and acreage, relative to claims on the federal government., 1 volume.
- List, n.d., of the first arrangement of military claims due the officers and soldiers of Virginia in the continental line, including warrant number, name, and acreage, relative to claims on the federal government., 1 volume.